<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the Church of St. Mary le Bow to the Societies for the Reformation of Manners, Octob. 4, 1697 / by Samuel Bradford.</title>
            <author>Bradford, Samuel, 1652-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08844600</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08844600</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41948</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29107)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41948)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1277:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the Church of St. Mary le Bow to the Societies for the Reformation of Manners, Octob. 4, 1697 / by Samuel Bradford.</title>
                  <author>Bradford, Samuel, 1652-1731.</author>
                  <author>Societies for the Reformation of Manners.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B. Aylmer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezra X, 3-4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41948:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the Church of St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> TO THE <hi>SOCIETIES</hi> FOR Reformation of Manners, <hi>Octob.</hi> 4. 1697.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL BRADFORD,</hi> Rector of the ſaid Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41948:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41948:2"/>
            <head>TO THE SOCIETIES FOR <hi>Reformation of MANNERS,</hi> In the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS I firſt Preach'd, ſo I now Print the following Sermon at Your Requeſt; though I am ſenſible that I can add nothing new, to what hath been already Publiſh'd by my Brethren, who went before me on this Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion;
<pb facs="tcp:41948:3"/>from whom You have had that juſt Encouragement which Your Cauſe deſerves, and thoſe prudent Directions, which if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> follow, You cannot err in the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding which, I have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon, by conſidering that in ſuch a Caſe as this, the concurring Judgment and Approbation of many who think and ſay the ſame thing, may the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tend to the promoting Your Deſign, of which I freely own my ſelf an Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rager, and ſhall think I have done a good Work, if any thing I have offer'd in this Diſcourſe may contribute thereunto.</p>
            <p>I have taken care in this Caſe to do nothing raſhly or inconſiderately; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having weigh'd, as well as I could, the Arguments for, and the Objections againſt Your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking; the former of which do, in my Judgment, very much outweigh the latter.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Vicious</hi> Men ſhould declare open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt Your Attempt, is not at all to
<pb facs="tcp:41948:3"/>be wonder'd at: 'Tis what they reckon their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> as well as their <hi>Inclination</hi> to do. And if ſome who are truly <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous</hi> and <hi>Pious,</hi> have entertain'd any Prejudices likewiſe, 'tis not very ſtrange, ſince I believe hardly any <hi>Extraordinary</hi> and truly <hi>Generous</hi> Deſign was ever yet ſet on Foot in the World, but what was at the firſt ſuſpected either as <hi>Imprudent,</hi> or <hi>Impracticable,</hi> by Men of otherwiſe good Judgment and Meaning.</p>
            <p>However, there is this obſervable Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Cenſures which <hi>Bad,</hi> and which <hi>Good</hi> Men paſs upon You. The former do it from an Averſion to the <hi>End</hi> which you propoſe: The latter only doubt concerning the <hi>Means</hi> which you uſe; <hi>Doubt,</hi> I ſay, for after all 'tis generally no more, they being rather ſhy of enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging themſelves, than forward to cenſure thoſe who do; nay, they cannot but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly wiſh You good Succeſs, whilſt they forbear to aſſiſt You; all which makes me conclude, that they are not perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of the Methods You take, or at leaſt have not thoroughly conſider'd them,
<pb facs="tcp:41948:4"/>and that when they have, they will alter their Judgments.</p>
            <p>That open Prophaneneſs and Lewdneſs ought to be ſuppreſt, they agree with you; (for what ſerious and good Man does not from his heart deteſt thoſe ſcandalous Practices, which You endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form?) The only Queſtion then is, How this may be effected? Now all that I would deſire of ſuch Perſons at preſent is, that they will not object againſt the courſe You take, till they can themſelves propoſe a better.</p>
            <p>But after all, What can be plauſibly objected againſt this, when, as the <hi>End</hi> is highly fit, nay, <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be purſued, ſo 'tis done by the Encouragement, and according to the Directions both of <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane Laws?</hi> So that what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in another Caſe, may be repeated in this, <hi>We know that the Law is good, if a Man uſe it lawfully.</hi> But of this I will add no more to what I have ſaid in the Sermon it ſelf.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41948:4"/>
            <p> Only upon this Occaſion, I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear expreſſing my ſatisfaction, in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>two</hi> hopeful Prognoſticks of a Better Generation to ſucceed the Preſent.</p>
            <p>One is, that Spirit of <hi>Genuine</hi> and <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity,</hi> which hath of late ſo evidently exerted it ſelf in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Numbers of the Eſtabliſh'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, eſpecially of the younger ſort of both Sexes; as appears not only by their attending the Publick Devotions, particularly the Holy Communion, with the greateſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs and Reverence; but alſo by a true Chriſtian Simplicity, Modeſty, Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Charity, Zeal and Courage, which, thoſe who have occaſion more intimately to Converſe with them, have frequently obſerv'd among them.</p>
            <p>The other is, that <hi>Zeal</hi> mixt with <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> which ſo many both of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Communion, and of thoſe who in ſome few things differ from them, have jointly expreſt, towards the ſuppreſſing of Vice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41948:5"/>
            <p> And I cannot but look upon it as the Duty of thoſe of our Function, to lay hold of every Opportunity of encouraging and directing Perſons, who are of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo well diſpos'd.</p>
            <p>That it may pleaſe Almighty God to bleſs and proſper theſe good Beginnings, and to give ſucceſs to your honeſt and worthy Endeavours, <hi>is the hearty Prayer of,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithful Friend and Servant, <hi>SAMUEL BRADFORD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41948:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ezra X.</hi> Part of the <hi>3d.</hi> and the <hi>4th.</hi> Verſe.</bibl>
                  <p>Now therefore let us make a Covenant with our God, —according to the Counſel of my Lord, and of thoſe that tremble at the Commandment of our God, and let it be done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law. Ariſe, for this matter belongeth unto thee; we alſo will be with thee; be of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and do it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SUCH is the Fulneſs of the Holy Scripture, both with reſpect to Directions and Precepts, as well as Inſtances and Examples, that in whatever Caſe we ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult them, we cannot want either the one, or the other, for our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and Encouragement. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to make it appear, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41948:6"/>which I have now read, are very well adapted to the Cauſe of our preſent Meeting.</p>
            <p>The Occaſion of them was this. The <hi>Jews</hi> having been detain'd in Captivity during the ſpace of Seventy Years, it pleas'd God at laſt, according to what he had foretold by his Prophets, to ſtir up the Heart of the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> to diſmiſs them to their own Countrey.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing they did after their return, was, what very well became them, to prepare an Altar whereon to offer up their daily Sacrifices to the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; proceeding next to Rebuild their Temple; which accordingly, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Oppoſition they met with from their Enemies, by the Bleſſing of God they Finiſh'd and Dedicated.</p>
            <p>After theſe things, as we read <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. <hi>Ezra,</hi> the Writer of this Book, obtain'd a Commiſſion from the <hi>Perſian</hi> King to go up to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to ſet in order and ſupply what was amiſs or wanting there; particularly to Beautify the Houſe of God, and to carry thither a very Noble Preſent from the King, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41948:6"/>and the Province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> for the Service of the Temple, and of the God who dwelt therein; and not only ſo, but likewiſe <hi>to ſet Magiſtrates and Judges</hi> over the People, even <hi>ſuch as knew the Laws of God;</hi> ordering alſo, That <hi>thoſe who did not know them, ſhould be taught by</hi> Ezra and his Brethren: To which large Commiſſion this Sanction was annexed by the King, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.26. <hi>Whoſoever will not do the Law of thy God, and the Law of the King, let judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be executed ſpeedily upon him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be unto death, or to baniſhment, or to confiſcation of goods, or to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Ezra</hi> was a Perſon well qualified for receiving ſuch a ſpecial Commiſſion, is apparent, by the Character given of him in the ſame Chapter, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. That <hi>he was a ready Scribe in the Law of Moſes, which the Lord God of Iſrael had given.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 10. that <hi>he had prepar'd his heart to ſeek the Law of the Lord, and to do it, and to teach in Iſrael Statutes and Judgements.</hi> And therefore the King himſelf, in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41948:7"/>to him, ſalutes him, by the Title of <hi>Prieſt and Scribe of the Law of the God of Heaven, ver.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>The Office and Buſineſs of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Scribe</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi> was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Knowledge of God's Law, and to teach it to the People; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly the very Copy which we have of the Law of God, and of the Prophets in the Old Teſtament, is generally ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to have been preſerv'd and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us by this <hi>Ezra,</hi> together with the Hiſtory of his own Times, wrote by himſelf.</p>
            <p>Such a Man as this was qualified to Execute the King's Commiſſion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the true intent of it, and is in this Caſe to be conſider'd both as a <hi>Prieſt</hi> and a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in one Perſon.</p>
            <p>In the ſequel of the Hiſtory we find he was faithful and punctual to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he had receiv'd. He firſt choſe out proper Companions, deliver'd the Offerings into their hands, kept a ſolemn Faſt with them, in order to the implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Protection of God in the way they were going; arriv'd ſafely at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41948:7"/>
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and after Three days Reſt, deliver'd up his Charge, and produc'd his Commiſſion, as we read <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>But when this was done, ſome of the Chief of the <hi>Jews</hi> came to him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd him of a great Tranſgreſſion which divers of their Nation had been and were ſtill guilty of. Thus we read Chap. 9.1, 2. <hi>The Princes came to me, ſaying, The people of Iſrael and the prieſts, and the Levites have not ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the people of the lands, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to their abominations: — For they have taken of their daughters for themſelves, and for their ſons; ſo that the holy ſeed have mingled themſelves with the people of thoſe lands; yea, the hand of the princes and rulers hath been chief in this treſpaſs.</hi> Where we ſee, that ſome of the <hi>Princes</hi> themſelves, thoſe who were Men of Chief Note and Place among the <hi>Jews,</hi> did not think it below them to turn <hi>Informers</hi> in a caſe of this Nature, however ſcandalous that Term may appear to ſome in our days. Nay, obſerve their <hi>Impartiality</hi> and their <hi>Courage</hi> at once; they did this, when ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41948:8"/>of their own Rank and Quality, when the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> were chief among the Tranſgreſſors.</p>
            <p>Upon this <hi>Information, Ezra,</hi> like a Pious and Good Man, in the firſt place expreſt his Senſe of this Evil Practice, by all the Signs which were cuſtomary among that People. For <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>he rent his garment, and his mantle, and pluckt off the hair of his head, and of his beard, and ſat down aſtonied;</hi> which when the people ſaw, 'tis ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. That <hi>every one that trembled at the words of the God of Iſrael, aſſembled unto him.</hi> Both he and all who had a ſenſe of the Authority of God's Law, were, it ſeems, deeply affected with the Tranſgreſſion of their Countreymen; they did not account it a ſlight matter to obſerve the Iniquity of others, though themſelves were innocent, but laid it very ſeriouſly to heart.</p>
            <p>Thus he ſat till the time of the <hi>Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sacrifice,</hi> and then, as it became the <hi>Prieſt</hi> of the Lord, ver. 5. <hi>he fell upon his knees, ſpread out his hands unto God,</hi> and made Supplication for the People. You may read his Prayer at your leiſure,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41948:8"/>in the remaining part of that Chapter; in which he repreſents in very pathetical Expreſſions, the Goodneſs and Patience of God on the one hand, with the Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Diſingenuity of the <hi>Jews</hi> on the other hand</p>
            <p>What follow'd upon this Prayer of <hi>Ezra</hi> we have in this Chapter, (<hi>Chap.</hi> 10.) out of which my Text is taken; where we read, <hi>Ver.</hi> 1. That <hi>when</hi> Ezra <hi>had prayed, and when he had confeſſed, weeping and caſting himſelf down before the houſe of God,</hi> (obſerve all along what a ſenſe this Good Man had of publick Treſpaſſes) <hi>there aſſembled unto him out of Iſrael a very great congregation of men, and women, and children; for the people wept very ſore.</hi> If the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſet themſelves heartily to reform Impiety and Wickedneſs, the <hi>People</hi> are apt to be influenced more than would eaſily be imagined without a trial. 'Twas ſo in this Inſtance, and I doubt not but it will be ſo, where ever the Experiment is fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made.</p>
            <p>Well! out of this Multitude one ſtood up, Ver. 2. <hi>Shechaniah</hi> by Name, <hi>the ſon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41948:9"/>of Jehiel, one of the ſons of Elam, and he anſwered and ſaid unto Ezra, We have treſpaſſed againſt our God, and have taken ſtrange wives of the people of the land; yet now there is hope in Iſrael concerning this thing.</hi> There is, in truth, always hope, where People are diſpoſed towards Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Amendment; the Infinite Goodneſs of the Divine Nature is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ground of Hope, whenſoever we render our ſelves capable of Mercy. He ſpeaks in the Plural Number, <hi>We have treſpaſſed,</hi> doing it in the Name of the People, though he was not himſelf guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as appears highly probable from the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Verſe of this Chapter, where among the guilty, who are reckoned by Name, this <hi>Shechaniah</hi> is not mentioned, though both his Father <hi>Jehiel,</hi> and five of his Father's Brethren are nam'd among th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that had taken ſtrange Wives: So that he was not barely innocent in this matter, but <hi>remarkably</hi> ſo, as not having been tempted and drawn in by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or Example of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>areſt Reia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And indeed ſuch an one it well becomes to appear forward its a buſineſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41948:9"/>of this nature, who is himſelf perfectly clear of thoſe Vices he would reform in others; he will with the better Grace, and the juſter Aſſurance act in ſuch a Caſe.</p>
            <p>But what was it, which he advis'd? Why, that we have in the words of my Text; <hi>Now therefore let us make a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with our God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus I have led you to the Text, by giving a very particular account of the Occaſion of it; becauſe throughout this whole Hiſtory there are, as you may have obſerv'd, many fair hints given us to our preſent purpoſe. In the reading of it, I purpoſely omitted one paſſage in the third Verſe, which expreſſes the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Reformation which was to be made at that time, <hi>viz. to put away all the Wives,</hi> (that is, their ſtrange Outlandiſh Wives) <hi>and ſuch as were born of them;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are not directly concern'd in the Law which was given to the <hi>Jews</hi> with reſpect to that matter. When God choſe out the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for his peculiar People, he ſaw it neceſſary to make a Separation between them and the Heathen, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41948:10"/>the old Inhabitants of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> leſt they ſhould be drawn into the Sin of Idolatry, to which they were ſo extremely prone; and this he did by many expreſs Laws to that purpoſe, among which this was one, Deut. 7.3. <hi>Neither ſhalt thou make marriages with them; thy daughter thou ſhalt not give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſon, nor his daughter ſhalt thou take unto thy ſon.</hi> This was judg'd ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for that People, that ſuch Marriages were not only utterly unlawful to be made by them, but were null if they were made; as appears by the Hiſtory of this matter, both in the Books of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> And if God, who is the Supreme Lord and Governor of the World, ſaw it fit to give a ſuch a Law, there can be no diſpute concerning their Duty to comply with it. However, this being only a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitive,</hi> not a <hi>Moral</hi> Law, it is obligatory to no other People but to thoſe to whom it was given; although perhaps it may not misbecome any Nation whatſoever, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing true Religion, to forbid Marriage with Idolaters, by a Law of their own, for fear of the ill Conſequences of it; As
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41948:10"/>in one inſtance, namely, that of our Princes, our Law makers have now thought fit to do, after a long and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Experience we have had of the Evils that attend ſuch Alliances. But that by the way. It may ſuffice to our preſent purpoſe, that the <hi>Jews</hi> had been guilty of a notorious Tranſgreſſion of the Divine Law given to them, and therefore were obliged to reform themſelves in that particular.</p>
            <p>But to come to the Words themſelves, as they may concern us, as well as the <hi>Jews. Now therefore,</hi> &amp;c. You may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in them theſe <hi>Six</hi> Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in the Caſe of publick and prevailing Tranſgreſſion, it was thought fit for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to aſſociate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine together, to engage themſelves and one another, to endeavour a Reformation of the Manners of their Country. <hi>Now therefore let us make a covenant with our God;</hi> that is, let us ſolemnly oblige our ſelves and one another, as one Body, thus to do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they were influenc'd to do thus, and directed in their doing it, by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41948:11"/>thoſe who had the Knowledge of God's Law, a Reverence for his Authority, and a Fear of his Power and Juſtice. <hi>Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the counſel of my Lord,</hi> that is, of <hi>Ezra,</hi> who was a <hi>Scribe</hi> of the Law of God, and perfectly inſtructed in it; <hi>and of thoſe that tremble at the Commandment of God;</hi> that is, let us do thus, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Advice thou haſt already inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to us by thy Humiliation, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and Prayer, with the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of all ſuch as have join'd with thee in humbling themſelves, and begging the Favour of God, as being ſenſible of his Diſpleaſure, and fearing the effects of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Law of God, and of their Country, was propos'd as the Rule by which their whole proceeding in this Caſe ſhould be guided. <hi>Let it be done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law;</hi> that is, let the Law of God given by <hi>Moſes</hi> be our Rule.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That this Work of Reformation was reckon'd to be the more eſpecial Charge and Buſineſs of thoſe, who preſided and govern'd both in Church and State. <hi>Ariſe; for this matter belongeth unto thee;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41948:11"/>as if he had ſaid, Thou art both qualified and commiſſion'd to direct and command us in this buſineſs, as having the Skill and the Authority both of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That the People alſo, in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Stations, and according to their ſeveral Capacities, were reſolv'd to aſſiſt and encourage their Governors, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Attempts they ſhould make to this purpoſe. <hi>We alſo will be with thee; be of good courage.</hi> He might well promiſe this for himſelf; and ſeeing the behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of ſo great a Multitude, he might reaſonably preſume the ſame for them, that each of them would afford his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to <hi>Ezra</hi> in ſo good, ſo laudable, and ſo neceſſary an Undertaking.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That open confeſſing publick Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and Supplicating for the Mercy of God, and for Grace to amend what was amiſs, was not thought ſufficient to excuſe either the Prieſts, or the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or the People, from doing their parts towards the obtaining what they deſir'd. <hi>Ariſe, be of good courage, and do it;</hi> that is, Having now kneel'd before
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41948:12"/>God, and offer'd up thy Supplications, Ariſe, ſtand up, and do what farther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes thee; and let neither the Number, nor the Conſiderableneſs of any Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors among us diſcourage thee; thou wilt not want the Aſſiſtance either of God or Man.</p>
            <p>The Time allotted for ſuch a Diſcourſe as this, will not permit me to enlarge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of theſe Obſervations; yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I think them all appoſite to our preſent Deſign, I ſhall endeavour briefly to illuſtrate each of them, and as I go along, apply them to the Purpoſe of this Aſſembly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is obſervable, That in the caſe of publick and prevailing Tranſgreſſion, it was thought fit for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate and Combine together, to engage themſelves, and one another, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a Reformation of the Manners of their Country. <hi>Now therefore let us make a covenant with our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There had been an open violation of an expreſs Law of God, of which ſeveral of all Ranks among them had been guilty.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41948:12"/>Now in oppoſition to theſe, 'tis ſaid, That <hi>a very great congregation aſſembled unto Ezra out of Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>Shechaniah,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both for himſelf and them, perſuades to the entring into a ſolemn Obligation to amend what had been amiſs among them.</p>
            <p>And the like we find in other Inſtances in the Holy Scriptures. Thus when there had been a general defection from the Law of God immediately after it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the Peoples making and worſhipping the Golden Calf, <hi>Moſes,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſeverely rebuked <hi>Aaron</hi> for complying with the Peoples folly, <hi>ſtood in the gate of the camp, and ſaid, Who is on the Lord's ſide, let him come unto me;</hi> upon which 'tis ſaid, that <hi>all the ſons of Levi gather'd themſelves unto him,</hi> Exod. 32.26. 'Tis true, the way in which they proceeded againſt the Tranſgreſſors, is not to be imitated by us, ſuch Methods being proper for that People, as are not for all others: But the <hi>Levites</hi> joining to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as one Body, to do what God and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould direct them, towards the ſuppreſſing the Idolatry which had ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41948:13"/>ſuddenly and ſo generally prevail'd, was what very well became them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves our imitation.</p>
            <p>I might again inſtance in what was done in the Reign of King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 Kings 22.8. Upon the High Prieſt's finding the Book of the Law, and ſending it to the King, he found by peruſing it, that the Nation had notoriouſly tranſgreſt the Precepts gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven therein, and were thereby expoſed to the juſt diſpleaſure of Almighty God; upon which, <hi>Chap.</hi> 23.1, 2, 3. <hi>He imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſent, and gathered unto him all the Elders of Judah, and of Jeruſalem; and he went up into the houſe of the Lord, and all the men of Judah, and all the inhabitants of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem with him, and the Prieſts, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and all the people both ſmall and great, and he read in their ears all the words of the book; and the King made a Covenant before the Lord, to walk after the Lord, and to keep his Commandments, and his Teſtimonies, and his Statutes, with all their heart, and with all their ſoul; — and all the people ſtood to the Covenant;</hi> in vertue of which, (as it follows in that Chapter) ſuch a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41948:13"/>Reformation was made, as had not been from the days of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to that time.</p>
            <p>And ſuch a Practice is very reaſonable; there being no other way likely to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Wickedneſs, when it is grown to an head, but for a conſiderable Body of ſuch eſpecially as are untainted with it, to ſet themſelves in open oppoſition and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to it. Single Attempts will prove too weak in ſuch a caſe; whereas the joint and unanimous Endeavours of many, who will encourage and aſſiſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will make Iniquity both aſham'd and afraid to ſhew it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And upon this account, I cannot but juſtify and commend your having form'd your ſelves into orderly and regular So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, for the more effectual carrying on that good Work which you have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken. 'Tis no other thing than what is conſtantly done without offence in Caſes of <hi>Secular</hi> Concernment; Prudence teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Experience confirming, as Men of Buſineſs in the World do well know, that no uſeful Deſign is ſo advantageouſly and thoroughly carried on by <hi>ſingle</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as by <hi>Companies.</hi> How many Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41948:14"/>are for that reaſon embodied throughout this Kingdom, for the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on particular Trades and Profeſſions? Nay, how many meer Voluntary Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are formed Yearly in this City, and aſſemble in this Church, as you now do, for the promoting good Correſpondence and Friendſhip among Neighbours or Countrymen? And why ſhould we not be as wiſe, and as zealous, in promoting the Honour of God, the Intereſts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Spiritual and Eternal Welfare of Mankind, nay, and the beſt Intereſts of the Kingdom we belong to, as we are in promoting any of our Secular Intereſts or Deſigns? No other reaſon, that I know of, can be aſſigned why we are not ſo, but becauſe <hi>the Children of this world are wiſer in their generation than the children of light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can I ſee any juſt Exception to be made againſt your Societies in particular, rather than againſt any of the reſt; ſince upon due Enquiry I am well ſatisfied, that they are under the Encouragement and Direction of Perſons, whoſe Prudence, as well as Piety, is unqueſtionable; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41948:14"/>ſince your Proceedings are guided by the Laws both of God and Man. But of that more under the following Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the next place therefore, I obſerv'd from the Text, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were influenc'd to take this Courſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in their doing it, by thoſe who had the knowledge of God's Law, a reverence for his Authority, and a fear of his Power and Juſtice. For ſo the Text ſays, <hi>Let us make a covenant with our God,— according to the counſel of my lord,</hi> (namely of <hi>Ezra) and of thoſe that tremble at the commandment of our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was by the Suggeſtion of <hi>Ezra,</hi> and thoſe who join'd with him in his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and Prayer, that <hi>Shechaniah</hi> made this Motion; and it was a thorough ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the Law of God, which mov'd <hi>Ezra;</hi> as it was a juſt fear of God's Diſpleaſure, and an awful reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence toward his Majeſty (expreſs'd by <hi>trembling at the commandment of God</hi>) which excited the Congregation. And there can be no doubt, but that all who were concern'd for this Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41948:15"/>and thus excited to attempt it, were ready to follow the Directions of <hi>Ezra,</hi> and to be guided by the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Counſels of the wiſeſt and beſt men among them, in the proſecuting their Deſign.</p>
            <p>They were the very ſame Principles which ſtir'd up <hi>Joſiah,</hi> in that other caſe I mention'd. It was his <hi>reading the book of the Law,</hi> which had, it ſeems, been utterly neglected, and almoſt loſt from among them, that put the King upon ſending to enquire of God, what he ſhould do; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.11, 12, 13. who in his Anſwer to him, commends him, for that <hi>his heart was tender, and he humbled himſelf before the Lord, when he heard what he had ſaid,</hi> in that Book. ver. 19.</p>
            <p>An awful regard for the Law of God, and a tender-hearted, humble, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate Concern for its being obey'd both by our ſelves and others, are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions highly commended in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writers. <hi>To this Man will I look,</hi> ſaith God by his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Iſa. 66.2. <hi>Even to him who is poor, and of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41948:15"/>a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my word.</hi> And 'tis nothing but the want of ſuch a Temper, that can make Men either go on careleſly in violating God's Laws themſelves, or behold others doing ſo, without uſing their Endeavours to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them.</p>
            <p>For God is infinitely above us, and we are intirely at his diſpoſal, as being the Work of his Hands, and under the conſtant care of his Providence; ſo that 'tis very fit, that he ſhould give us Laws, and that we ſhould reckon our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſtricteſt Obligations to be govern'd by them.</p>
            <p>How can the wilful and obſtinate Offender think to eſcape unpuniſh'd, whilſt he violates thoſe Laws which are Eſtabliſh'd by indiſputable Authority, backt with uncontroulable Power?</p>
            <p>But that which ſhould yet farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our Reverence towards them, is, That they are founded alſo upon the eternal and unalterable Rules of Juſtice and Equity. 'Tis true, there were ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>poſitive</hi> Laws given by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> which are uſually ſaid to be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41948:16"/>good, becauſe commanded; (though to that People, and in thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, God, no doubt, knew that it was good to give them;) and 'tis remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable, that it was even one of thoſe <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive</hi> Laws, which <hi>Ezra</hi> and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that join'd with him ſhew'd ſuch a regard to at that time. How inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable then are we, if we do not Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thoſe Laws, which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us in the very <hi>Frame and Conſtitution of our Nature,</hi> and which we can never tranſgreſs, without contradicting the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Senſe of our own Minds, and Violating our Conſciences!</p>
            <p>And ſuch in truth are the Laws, for the Execution of which you now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; <hi>Viz.</hi> Thoſe whereby we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to Reverence the Name of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, to obſerve ſome certain fixt Times for his Publick Worſhip and Service, to preſerve our ſelves ſober and chaſt, free from thoſe Defilements and Diſorders of the Fleſh, which would be to our own great prejudice, and the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of our Neighbours. Who can doubt, whether ſuch Laws as theſe ought to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41948:16"/>be eſteem'd ſacred or not? And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently 'tis not to be wonder'd at, if thoſe among us who daily converſe with the Holy Scriptures, as well as with their own Minds, and are acquainted with the Precepts written both in the one and the other, and have at the ſame time a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard for the Authority of Almighty God, and <hi>tremble at his word,</hi> ſhould unite their Endeavours againſt the open and groſs violation of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But 'tis farther obſervable in the Text, That the Law of God, and of their Countrey, was propoſed as the Rule by which their whole proceeding in this caſe ſhould be guided. <hi>And let it be done according to the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was to the <hi>Jews</hi> both the Law of God, and the Municipal Law of their Countrey too. God was their King, and gave them their Laws immediately from Heaven, and therefore 'twas fit they ſhould have recourſe to theſe, whenever they ſet upon a Publick Reformation.</p>
            <p>As to other Nations, which are not ſo immediately under a Divine Legiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41948:17"/>there are firſt the Laws of God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Mankind in the very frame of their Nature, and reſulting from the Reaſon of Things, which oblige all the Children of Men, as being publiſh'd to all; and whereever God hath given any <hi>poſitive</hi> Laws over and above, thoſe to whom they are publiſh'd are equally obliged by them alſo. And in all other caſes, the Municipal Laws of each Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſo far as they do not contradict the Divine, are to be a Rule to all Ranks and Orders of men therein, eſpecially with reſpect to all their actions of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Concernment and Importance. For they are made by an Authority deriv'd from God, as all lawful humane Power is; and they are the very Bonds and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments of Society, which at firſt unite, and afterwards hold men in one Body; they are plainly the Conditions upon which any Countrey or Kingdom agree and oblige themſelves to act. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing can be more imprudent or dangerous to a Community, than either to make Laws that are not fit to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, or not to ſee to the Execution of thoſe that are made.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41948:17"/>
            <p> As to our own Country, thanks be to God, we live under the Direction of wife and wholeſome Laws, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly thoſe Laws of our Countrey which you endeavour to have executed, are ſuch as are undoubtedly agreeable to the Laws of God.</p>
            <p>As for inſtance; Do the Laws of our Realm ſtrictly forbid and puniſh all <hi>prophane Swearing and Curſing?</hi> Does not the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nay of <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf, do the ſame?</p>
            <p>Do the Laws of our Countrey appoint a certain <hi>Day</hi> for the publick ſolemn Worſhip of Almighty God? God by <hi>Moſes</hi> did the ſame to the <hi>Jews;</hi> and our Bleſſed Saviour and his Apoſtles have by their Example obliged us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to the like practice; and this alſo very agreeably to the Light of Nature, and the Dictates of right Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Do the Laws of this Kingdom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the exorbitances of an <hi>intemperate</hi> and <hi>unclean</hi> Life, inflicting Penalties up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that either abuſe themſelves, or corrupt others in theſe matters? No man who reads the Holy Scriptures of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41948:18"/>the Old and New Teſtament, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults the Dictates of his own Conſcience, can be ignorant, that this is agreeable to the Will of God diſcover'd both by <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would fain know, why we, who are ſo jealous with reſpect to the Honour of our Laws in all other caſes, ſhould not be at leaſt equally ſo in the caſes I have now mention'd. Are thoſe Laws only fit to lie dormant, which were deſign'd directly for the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and promoting <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> among us? Is it fit to exact thoſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties which our Laws inflict, where one man injures another in his Eſtate or his Reputation? But not where our Maker is openly affronted and injured by his Creatures? Is it fit to put thoſe Laws in Execution, which are made for the Safety or the Honour of our Prince? And not thoſe alſo which are made for the Honour and the Intereſt of him who is <hi>King of kings, and Lord of lords?</hi> In a word; Can we with a good Conſcience look on, and ſee no regard had to thoſe Laws of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41948:18"/>which, if duly obſerv'd, would have a ſpecial Tendency to promote the ſpiritual good of our Brethren, as well as their temporal, and to preſerve the good order, the peace, and the ſafety of the whole Body? There can, I am well aſſur'd, be no reply made in this caſe.</p>
            <p>All therefore that I ſhall add upon this Head is, to put you in mind of what I know you have already among your Directions and Rules, <hi>viz.</hi> That whatſoever you do in this whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, be as our Text expreſſes it, <hi>done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the law;</hi> that you never in the leaſt exceed its bounds and meaſures; but on the other hand, that you allow for every reaſonable and equitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, ever inclining rather to the ſide of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> than of rigid <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed;</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Work of Reformation was reckon'd to be the more eſpecial Charge and Buſineſs of thoſe who preſided and govern'd both in Church and State. <hi>Ariſe; for this matter belongeth unto
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41948:19"/>thee;</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Ezra,</hi> who as he was a <hi>Prieſt of God,</hi> and a <hi>Scribe of his Law,</hi> ſo he came alſo with a Special <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarch.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of God, and the <hi>Scribes</hi> of his Law, there can be no doubt made. The Law is given to them in eſpecial Charge, and they are to make it their conſtant endeavour to inſtruct the People in it, and by all means to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade and excite to a faithful Obedience to it.</p>
            <p>And as to <hi>Governors</hi> or <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> both Reaſon and Scripture aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, That <hi>rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil;</hi> that <hi>they are the miniſters of God to us for good;</hi> that <hi>if we do that which is evil, we may be afraid of them,</hi> becauſe <hi>they bear not the ſword in vain, but are the miniſters of God, revengers to execute wrath upon them that do evil,</hi> Rom. 13.3, 4. And again, That our <hi>Governors,</hi> whether <hi>Supreme</hi> or <hi>Subordinate,</hi> are <hi>ſent by God for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13, 14. For which reaſon they are ſometimes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41948:19"/>
               <hi>Gods,</hi> becauſe they are God's Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents, having an Authority derived from the Great Lord and Governor of all. Their great Buſineſs therefore is, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Honour of him whoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they are inveſted with, and whoſe Image they bear, together with the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and happineſs of the People whom they govern, keeping all in good Order, ſo that under them their Subjects may <hi>lead</hi> not only <hi>quiet and peaceable Lives,</hi> but <hi>in all Godlineſs and Honeſty</hi> alſo; which Ends cannot be attain'd without making and executing ſuch Laws as may preſerve and promote Piety and Virtue, the Fear of God, together with Juſtice and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety among Men.</p>
            <p>And as the Nature and Deſign of their <hi>Office</hi> require all this of them; ſo they are under a ſpecial Obligation to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, by the <hi>Oath of God</hi> with which they have bound themſelves, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſure be intended to engage them to the Obſervance and Execution of all the Laws of their Country, with an excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only of thoſe, in which the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and the Welfare of their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41948:20"/>Country are moſt nearly and deeply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted.</p>
            <p>Thanks be to God, there are many Magiſtrates among us, particularly in this City, who ſeem to have a good ſenſe of this upon their Minds, and, to their Honour, have ſhew'd themſelves for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward upon all occaſions to act according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. May God Almighty bleſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Endeavours, and increaſe their Number; and may he excite all Orders of Men among us, from the higheſt to the loweſt, to engage heartily and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly in ſo good a Work.</p>
            <p>But the next Particular <hi>I</hi> obſerv'd in the Text was, That</p>
            <p n="5">5. The People alſo, in their reſpective Stations, and according to their ſeveral Capacities, were reſolv'd to encourage and aſſiſt their Governors in whatſoever Attempts they ſhould make to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>We alſo will be with thee; be of good courage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He who ſaid this in his own Name and the Peoples, ſeems to have been nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Prieſt</hi> nor <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> but one of the Common People, his Family being
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41948:20"/>reckon'd a little after in this Chapter, (<hi>Ver.</hi> 25, 26.) among <hi>the people of Iſrael</hi> only; ſo that, as I obſerv'd in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Diſcourſe, That the <hi>Princes</hi> did not think it below them, to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> in a Caſe of this nature; ſo it was not it ſeems look'd upon as an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent</hi> or <hi>Officious</hi> Act, a medling out of his <hi>Sphere</hi> or <hi>Station,</hi> for a <hi>private</hi> Man to encourage and aſſiſt <hi>Ezra,</hi> nay, to move and excite him to the Work of Reformation.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed can any one who thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiders this matter, eaſily fall into ſuch a miſtake. For beſides that the Magiſtrate very often wants the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of thoſe that are under him, to excite his Vigour, and to ſtrengthen his Hands in the Execution of Laws up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on numerous, bold, wealthy, or great Offenders; it is moreover impoſſible in very many inſtances, that he ſhould exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them at all, unleſs, according to the Deſign and Intimation of the Laws them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, due Information be firſt given him againſt thoſe that violate them, which muſt generally be the part of ſuch among
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41948:21"/>the Common People, as being themſelves Innocent, yet are frequently converſant with Tranſgreſſors. In ſo much, that if a wiſe and good Magiſtrate ſhould have never ſo great a ſhare of Zeal and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, it would avail nothing, unleſs others do their part alſo.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, Are there not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and eaſier Methods for carrying on a Publick Reformation, than for one Neighbour to inform the Magiſtrate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another; and ſuch as a good-natur'd modeſt Man, and an humble Chriſtian, would rather chuſe to be engaged in?</p>
            <p>I anſwer; There is no queſtion, but that ſeveral other things may and ought to be done, in order to the reforming the Manners of a Nation. As particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly,</p>
            <p>That every good Man ſhould take eſpecial care to give an Example of all manner of Virtue and Piety to others, that according to the Precept of our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, Matth. 5.16. <hi>his light ſhould ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee his good works, and glorify his heavenly Father</hi> by an imitation of him.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41948:21"/>
            <p> Moreover, that every Parent of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Maſter of Servants, ſhould carefully inſtruct and govern his Family, ſetting up the conſtant Worſhip of God in his Houſe, inſtructing all that belong to him in the Principles of Religion, and obliging them to behave themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly whilſt they are under his care, according to the practice of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the <hi>Father of the Faithful,</hi> to whom God himſelf gave Teſtimony, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. That <hi>he knew him, that he would command his children, and his houſhold after him,</hi> ſo that <hi>they ſhould keep the way of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. And I doubt not, but that the want of this care in the Heads of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, eſpecially in this laſt Generation, has been a very great occaſion of the Looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the preſent Age; and that this would be one very effectual means of mending the ſtate of Things among us, if all thoſe who are concern'd would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly diſcharge their Duty in this reſpect. It would in a great meaſure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the care of the Magiſtrate, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Execution of Laws againſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and Immorality in a good degree needleſs.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41948:22"/>
            <p> A further means of Reformation would be, for every ſerious Chriſtian to take the courage in all Company, where ever he hath a fair Occaſion or Opportunity given him, to recommend Piety and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to run down Wickedneſs and Vice, and to reprove and rebuke, in modeſt and friendly manner, thoſe whom he obſerves openly to tranſgreſs and offend; and if ſeveral in the ſame Company, who are themſelves well diſpoſed, would conſpire to back and aſſiſt one another in ſo doing, I doubt not but that much good might be done this way.</p>
            <p>And there is no queſtion, but that every modeſt and good Man heartily wiſhes, that there were no need of any other method than theſe.</p>
            <p>But after all, it muſt be ſaid, That there are abundance of Caſes, in which theſe Courſes will not do the buſineſs; and where they will not, 'tis but reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, nay 'tis our Duty to proceed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and if the good Nature and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty of any good Man ſhould tempt him to neglect his Duty in ſuch a Caſe, yet if he have an hearty Concern, and right
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41948:22"/>Chriſtian Zeal for the Honour of God, the Good of his Brother, and the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his Country, theſe will enable him to overcome his Reluctancy.</p>
            <p>What thoſe Caſes are, Prudence and Experience will eaſily diſcover; as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, when prophane and lewd Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are grown Bold and Impudent, ſo as to deſpiſe all Reproof, and ſpurn at Admonitions, being by uſe and practice ſo hardened, that nothing is like to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt them in their evil Courſes, but the down-right Execution of wholſome Laws, by the Authority and Power of the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour, who knew well how to rebuke, either mildly or ſharply, as the Caſe requir'd, hath plainly ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to us, that there are ſome Sinners got beyond reproof, and not to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted that way, Matth. 7.6. <hi>Give not that which is holy to dogs, neither caſt ye your pearls before ſwine, leſt they tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple them under their feet, and turn again and rent you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in truth, the Practices which you have ſet your ſelves to reform, are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41948:23"/>ſuch, as nothing but an intolerable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all things Sacred, and an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence to Virtue and Sobriety can bring Men to.</p>
            <p>Is it to be imagin'd, for inſtance, That thoſe who keep lewd, or otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Houſes, wherein all ſorts of Men, and more eſpecially the Youth of the Nation are corrupted, debauched, and ruin'd, both in Body, and Soul, and Eſtate, will be prevail'd upon to forego and quit their diſhoneſt Gain by gentle and modeſt Reproofs? Or that thoſe who have ſo far thrown off all Shame, as to frequent ſuch places, will be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by meer perſuaſion?</p>
            <p>Is it to be ſuppos'd that the Man, who has ſo far diſcarded Humanity, as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to render himſelf a Beaſt, in the view of all his Neighbours, and to be diſtinguiſh'd as he walks the Streets, only by being unable to retain the Poſture of a Man, will be inſtructed into better Manners?</p>
            <p>Is it, laſtly, to be thought, that thoſe who have ſo far abandon'd all regard either to God or Man, as frequently to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41948:23"/>call upon their Maker to damn either themſelves or their Brethren, will ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily take a Rebuke kindly at your hands? Or, that others who ſo deſpiſe Almighty God and his Worſhip, as open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to miſuſe his Sacred Name, and to prophane that Day which is ſet apart for his Service, in defiance to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and plain Laws of God and their Country, will be reclaim'd by only tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them ſoftly that they do amiſs? I preſume not, and if any one be of another Opinion, he is at liberty to make the Experiment.</p>
            <p>If there be among any of theſe ſorts, ſuch as we may have reaſonable hopes of, as perhaps ſome few who have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a vile Habit of prophaning the Name of God by Oaths, which they utter in Common Diſcourſe unawares, theſe will either be reclaim'd when they ſee the Laws executed upon others, or elſe 'tis but fit that they ſhould fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Penalty and the Shame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="6">6. There is one Obſervation more which I made from the Text, and that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41948:24"/>is, That open confeſſing publick Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and praying for the Mercy of God, and for his Grace to amend what was amiſs, was not thought ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe either the Prieſt, or the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or the People, from doing their parts towards the obtaining what they deſir'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezra</hi> had been upon his Knees, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Sins of the People, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the Mercy and Favour of God towards them, in very pathetical Terms, and a large Congregation had join'd with him in all this; but this it ſeems was not enough; <hi>Shechaniah</hi> ſays to him, <hi>Ariſe, be of good courage, and do it.</hi> And accordingly we read, that he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately took his Advice; for it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>v</hi> 5. <hi>Then Ezra aroſe,</hi> namely, from off his Knees, <hi>and made the Chief-Prieſts, and Levites, and all Iſrael to ſwear, that they ſhould do according to this word; and they ſware;</hi> and according to this their Reſolution and Oath they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as appears by the ſequel of the Hiſtory.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41948:24"/>
            <p> Prayer is one proper Means to avert the Diſpleaſure of God from a ſinful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and hath been always uſed as ſuch by Pious Men, when they have liv'd where Iniquity abounded, and very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with good ſucceſs, as we find in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Inſtances in the <hi>Old Teſtament:</hi> But if it be not accompanied with ſuch At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts and Endeavours as are within our power, and are evidently conducive to the ſame End, it may juſtly paſs for the effect of Hypocriſy or Formality, and tend rather to provoke Almighty God, than to obtain his Favour toward us. For with what face can any one beg par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of God for the Tranſgreſſions of the Nation he lives in, without doing his part towards the amending them? How can he deſire that God would pour out a Spirit of Repentance and Reformation upon the Kingdom (which is probably one of the Petitions he offers up on ſuch an occaſion) unleſs he excite the ſame in himſelf, and others, as much as may be?</p>
            <p>And now to apply this laſt Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our ſelves, and therewith to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41948:25"/>this Diſcourſe. We have been for divers Years paſt offering up our Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to God; we have had our ſtated days of Solemn Faſting and Humiliation to this purpoſe; and among other things we have deſir'd, That God would be pleaſed by his Grace to reform whatever has been amiſs in the midſt of us, as well as that he would deliver us from our Enemies, and avert the Evils our Sins had expos'd us to; and hereby certainly we have laid our ſelves under a ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of adding our Endeavours to our Petitions.</p>
            <p>And we are farther engaged at this time by way of Gratitude alſo, ſince it hath pleas'd God ſo far to anſwer our Requeſts, as to prevent thoſe Evils we fear'd, and after a Tedious, Expenſive, and Bloody War, (in the midſt of which, Thanks be to God, we were deliver'd from feeling the ſevereſt effects of it) to reſtore to us the great Bleſſing of Peace.</p>
            <p>Now what can we do leſs, after all this, than to make a vigorous Effort, to root out thoſe Sins which ever did, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41948:25"/>ever will endanger our Peace and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, whilſt they prevail among us? How can we better teſtify and expreſs our Thankfulneſs to Almighty God, our Great Deliverer and Preſerver; or our Concern for the continuance of Peace and Tranquillity to our Nation, than in this way? The preſent Gracious Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Providence is both a Motive and Encouragement to us thus to do.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to ſpeak freely upon this Occaſion. We had once before in this Age a fair opportunity given us by Providence, for becoming a happy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; I mean when our Legal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Eſtabliſh'd Church, were re-ſetled, upon the Peaceable Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>But the remembrance of that Seaſon is attended with a very melancholy Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, namely, how groſly we abuſed the Goodneſs of God, and turn'd his Grace into Wantonneſs. Inſtead of a wiſe and ſober Improvement of ſo great a Bleſſing, 'tis too well known, that <hi>rioting and drunkenneſs, chambering and wantonneſs, ſtrife and envying,</hi> were the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41948:26"/>unhappy Effects of our Peace and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at that time.</p>
            <p>Neither can we be unacquainted, what a hand the Common Enemy has had in promoting Prophaneſs and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion among us ever ſince; as well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that nothing could ſo effectually promote their Intereſts, as firſt dividing us into Parties, and then ſowing the Seeds of Looſneſs and Licentiouſneſs as much as was poſſible among each Party. We are not now ignorant of their Devices, and I hope our Experience will make us wiſer and better for the time to come.</p>
            <p>We are now tried by Providence once again, how we will demean our ſelves; and 'tis not, methinks, to be deſpair'd of, but that all who are ſerious, and well diſpos'd in the Nation, may again unite and agree to promote the common Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of our Religion, and our Country. It ſeems to me a good Omen, that God hath ſtir'd up the hearts of ſo many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, to expreſs a concern and zeal for the ſuppreſſing Impiety and Vice; and that in proſecuting this Excellent Deſign, many of our Diſſenting Brethren
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41948:26"/>are join'd with thoſe of the Eſtabliſh'd Communion. 'Tis to be hoped, that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent converſing upon ſo good an Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as this, may be a means of removing all Unreaſonable Prejudices, and by degrees may beget a better Underſtanding, and a more favourable Opinion of each other. If our Zeal were but once turn'd towards the great things of Religion, in which we all agree, I am perſuaded that our Differences about leſs Matters would ſoon abate, and we might perhaps come to an agreement about them before we were aware.</p>
            <p>But to let that paſs. As far as we are agreed, <hi>Let us walk by the ſame Rule, let us mind the ſame thing.</hi> I mean, Let us with one conſent promote the common Intereſts of our Religion, and the Virtue of the Nation, of which we are all Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. <hi>Let us ariſe; be of good courage, and do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible, after all, that there are other Iniquities among us, beſides thoſe which the Law reaches, and ſuch as are highly provoking to God, and dangerous to the Kingdom; particularly,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41948:27"/>that baſe <hi>ſelfiſhneſs</hi> of Spirit which has ſo notoriouſly prevail'd and ſpread it ſelf like a Leproſie, in all Parties, and in all Ranks of Men among us. This is, in great meaſure, out of the power of the Law, and the Magiſtrate, and muſt be left to God alone to rectify, though it be a publick, and a very ſcandalous Sin. But the Sins you have ſet your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, you have found by Experience may be in ſome meaſure control'd; and 'tis worth the while for every good Man to carry the matter as far as 'tis in his power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And may that good God, who hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done ſo great things for us, direct and proſper your farther Endeavours; may he, by the power of his Grace and good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſtir up all Orders of men among us, to do their part towards the promoting the publick good, in this, and in all other caſes; May he continue Peace and Tranquillity both to our Church and State; May he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all our Differences, and make up our Breaches; May he bleſs and proſper his Church throughout the world, delivering
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41948:27"/>all its oppreſſed Members, increaſing Piety and Charity among all that profeſs the Chriſtian Name: And laſtly, May he cauſe Truth, Righteouſneſs, and Peace, the fear of his holy Name, together with all Virtue and Goodneſs to be propagated in all parts of the Earth, that his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom may come, and his will may be done on Earth as it is Heaven. Grant this, O heavenly Father, for thy Son Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom with thee, and the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit, be all Honour and Glory now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41948:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Printed for</hi> B. Aylmer <hi>at the</hi> Three Pigeons <hi>in</hi> Cornhill.</head>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the Aldermen and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> at St. <hi>Mary Le Bow,</hi> on <hi>Thurſday, Nov.</hi> 5. 1696. on <hi>Rom.</hi> III. 8. By <hi>Samuel Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Rector of the ſaid Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Family Religion:</hi> Or the Exerciſe of Prayer and Devotion in Private Families. By the late Reverend Dr. <hi>Paine,</hi> late Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>White Chappel.</hi> In 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 2 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd at St. <hi>Mary Le Bow</hi> to the Societies for Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>April</hi> 5. 1697. on <hi>Gal.</hi> IV. 18. By <hi>Lilly Butler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd at St. <hi>Mary Le Bow</hi> before the Lord Mayor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Faſt. On <hi>Nehem.</hi> IX. part of the 26th and 27th Verſes.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd at St. <hi>Lawrence Jury</hi> at the Election of the Lord Mayor, 1696. on <hi>Prov.</hi> XXIX. 2.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>James Lordell,</hi> March 27. 1694. on <hi>Rev.</hi> XIV. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Four laſt by</hi> Lilly Butler, <hi>Miniſter of St.</hi> Mary Aldermanbury.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41948:28"/>
            <p> Six Sermons, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Stedfaſtneſs in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Of Family Religion. Of Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Children. Of the Advantage of an Early Piety. By his Grace <hi>John,</hi> late Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſuaſive to Frequent Communion in the Holy Sacrament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Alſo by his Grace. Price bound 6 <hi>d.</hi> and ſtitcht 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Brief Expoſition on the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. To which is added the Doctrin of the Sacraments. By the Learned <hi>Iſaac Barrow,</hi> D. D. and late Maſter of <hi>Trinity College, Cambridge.</hi> (This on the Creed never before Publiſh'd.) In 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 4 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Practical Diſcourſes upon the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our latter End, and the Danger and Miſchief of Delaying Repentance. Alſo by Dr. <hi>Iſaac Barrow.</hi> In 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Four laſt things, <hi>viz.</hi> Death, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Heaven and Hell: Practically con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and applied. By <hi>W. Bates,</hi> D. D. In 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contemplations of Death and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.
<pb facs="tcp:41948:29"/>By the late Earl of <hi>Mancheſter.</hi> The 15th Edition. In 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Familiar Guide to the right and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Receiving of the Lord's Supper. Wherein alſo the Way and Method of our Salvation is briefly and plainly declared. By <hi>Theophilus Dorrington.</hi> Price 12 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Conference with an Anabaptiſt. In 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 12 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Theological Diſcourſe of Laſt Wills and Teſtaments. Price 12 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Seaſonable Vindication of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity. Being an Anſwer to this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Why do you believe the Doctrin of the Trinity?</hi> Collected from the Works of the moſt Reverend, Dr. <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> late Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> And the Right Reverend Dr. <hi>Edward Stilling-fleet,</hi> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> In 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price 12 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe three laſt by Dr.</hi> Aſheton <hi>of</hi> Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enham <hi>in</hi> Kent.</p>
            <p>Several ſmall Books againſt Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Prophaneſs, Blaſphemy, Curſing and Swearing. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo by Dr. <hi>Aſheton.</hi> Price 2 <hi>d.</hi> each; but ſomething cheaper to them that give away Numbers.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
